Guide to the John Folmar Monongahela River Steam Towboat Photograph Collection, 1870-1957 AIS.2019.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
John Folmar Monoghahela River Valley Steam Towboats Photographs
1870-1957
1910-1945
ULS Archives & Special Collections
AIS.2019.01
0.42 Linear Feet 1 box
John Kent Folmar was a professor at California University of Pennsylvania, President of the Monongahela River Buffs Association from 1980-1, 1990-2015, and editor of the MRBA newsletter, "Voice of the Mon" from 1981-2015. The collection includes photographs of towboats that plied the waterways of the Monongahela between 1870 and 1957.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acqusition Information
Gift of Dr. John Kent Folmar I on January 3, 2019.
Related Materials
Extensive use of the University of Wisconsin-Madison Libraries UW-La Crosse Historic Steamboat Photographs digital collection was employed in searching for particular vessels by name, their T numbers, and their histories; http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/LaCrosseSteamboat.
Additionally, the Way's Steam Towboat Directory by Frederick Way Jr. and Joseph W. Rutter (1990) provided the T number designations for the steamboats in this collection. Way, Frederick, and Joseph W Rutter. Way's Steam Towboat Directory. Ohio University Press, 2013.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. John Kent Folmar I, a professor at California University of Pennsylvania, was the leading figure of the Monongahela River Buffs Association from its founding in 1979 to 2015. He began his undergraduate education in Samford University in Alabama after having served in the Air National Guard during the Korean War. He would go on to teach history at Jones Valley before moving to the Military School in Mobile, Alabama to continue teaching. He began his graduate work as a teaching assistant at the University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, in 1963. By 1969, he began working at a professor at California University of Pennsylvania, where he would be department chair between 1976 and 1980. It was during this time he travelled to Greensboro and met the nascent Monongahela River Boat Association. He would serve as president from 1980-1981, and 1990-2015. He would incorporate aspects of his research in the MRBA into his Cal U classes before his retirement in 1999, and would go on to write dozens of articles and conduct lectures on the subject.
The MRBA was formed in 1979 between Bill Young, Ernie Gabler and Bill Bennett, with Dr. Folmar being an early addition. In 1986, the MRBA moved to Monongahela, PA, and opened their museum which contained artifacts, models, and other memorabilia of the river boat industry in West Virginia and western Pennsylvania. The purpose of the organization was to educate people about the region's first major industry, as well as the general culture, lore, and traditions of the Monongahela River Valley. This education would be done through the museum, and the quarterly release of a newsletter, "The Voice of the Mon", of which Dr. Folmar was an editor from 1981 to 2015. The museum would close in 2015, as would the MRBA be disbanded and the newsletter ended, but Dr. Folmar would publish "The Voices" with an appendix providing the organizations history in the years after.
Arrangement
The filing system for the Folmar Photograph collection has retained most of its original form. That is to say, original photograph dividers have been kept with the notes, which includes: name of vessel, name of owner/captain, date (if available), and T number designation in accordance with the Way's Steam Towboat Directory. All excess dividers and original indexes are kept in Folder 1: Index. All folders thereafter are arranged in alphabetical order with respect to the name of the vessel(s) in the photograph.
Scope and Content Note
Dating back to late 18th century, the Monongahela Valley was a center of river boat production in what was then the American North West. After massive public works to make the Monongahela more navigable and facilitate westward-expansion, between 1811 and 1888, over 3,000 steam boats would be produced from various boatyards throughout the region. By the turn of the 20th century, river traffic was frequent and modestly safe, if not as popular a transportation method as the concurrently growing railroad network. The largest contribution of this industry in the 20th century was plying the waterways with barges loaded with coal to fuel the growing steel industry in Pittsburgh and beyond. In recognition of this important industry in western Pennsylvanian history, the Monongahela River Buffs Association opened a museum in 1986 in Monongahela, PA, wherein artifacts, models, and photographs would be displayed for the viewing public until the museum closed in 2015. This collection is made up of one hundred and eight photographs of locally owned and operated steam-powered towboats, from between 1870 and 1957, kept for posterity.
- Index (Box 1, Folder 1)
- A.B. Sheets, Hillman Coal & Coke Co., T0005, 1921-1947; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Acorn, Consolidated Coal Co. (Combine), T0032, April 17, 1897; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Alicia, Brown Coal & Coke Col. T0101 and 0102, 1913-1926; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Aliquippa, Jones & Laughlin Co., T0103, 1914-1952; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Andrew Axton, Diamond Coal Co., T0128, 1903-1906; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 6)
- B.F. Fairless, Carnegie Illinois Steel Corp., T0186, 1935-1952; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
- B.F. Jones Co., Jones and Laughlin Co., T0187, 1907-1952; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Beacon, Pittsburgh Coal Co., T0209, 1917-1937; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Braddock, American Steel and Wire Co., T0291, 1916-1926; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Champion Coal, Combine, T0373, 1935-1954; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Charles R. Cox, US Steel Corp., T0385, 1948-1960; 2 item (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Charles T. Campbell, Campbell Trans. Co. +2 co. later, T0390, 1936-1955; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Charlie Clarke, W.H. Brown & Sons + 3 co. later, T0398, November 1911; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Collier, W.H. Brown/U.S. Steel Corp., T0464, 1914-1939; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Crescent, Pittsburgh Coal Co./J.K. Davison Bros., T0520, 1937-1952; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Cruiser, Brown's Line/Combine, T0530, 1923-1935; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Crusader, Combine, T0532, 1908; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Dewing and Sons, Dewing Lumber Co., T0596, 1894-1915; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Donora, American Steel/Carnegie Steel Co., T0622, 1924-1950; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Duquesne, U.S. Steel Corp., T0645, 1929-1964; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Edgar Thomson, Carnegie Steel Co., T0685, 1919-1953; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Fallie, McKinley Coal Co./Combine, T0794, 1894-1921; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 23)
- George Roberts, Horner & Roberts, T0929, 1870-1891; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Henry L. Laughlin, J&L Steel Co., T1088, 1905; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Harry L. Roemer, Monessen Coal and Coke Co./Hillman Trans. Co., T1090, 1936-1944; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Iron City, Iron City Sand Co., T1199, 1912-1948; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 27)
- J.E. Leonard, J.E. Leonard, Brownsville PA, T1243, 1903-1905; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 28)
- J.H. Hillman, Hillman Trans. Co., T1253, 1927-1951; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 29)
- J.H. McGrady, McGrady-Rodgers Co., T1255, 1927-1944; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 30)
- J.L. Perry, Carnegie-Illinois Steel Co., T1264, 1945-1957; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 31)
- James A. Rankin, J&L Steel Co., T1319, 1948-1952; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 32)
- James A. Lose, Carnegie-Illinois Steel Co., T1323, 1938-1948; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Joe Carter, Hillman twice/C. Zubik, T1383, March 6, 1940; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 34)
- John A. Ailes, Combine, T1442, 1892-1902; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 35)
- John W. Hubbart, Campbell Tans. Co. +2 co. later, T1444, 1920-1932; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Leona, Capt. R.J. Hiernaux, Charleroi, PA, T1571, 1929-1941; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Juniata, American Stele and Wire co., T1480, 1900-1925; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Little Fred, O'Neil Coal Co./Combine, T1605, 1881-1915; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Maggie, Samuel Clarke & Sons/James Jones/Combine, T1691, 1881-1902; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Marion, McClain Sand Co., Point Marion, PA T1723, November 21, 1923; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Mongah, Pittsburgh Coal Co., T1855, 1937-1957; 4 item (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Monitor, Diamond Coal and Coke Co./Carnegie Steel Co., T1860, 1907-1925; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Monongahela, Carnegie Steel Co./Ohio Barge Line, T1862, 1927-1955; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 44)
- William G. Glyde and Pacific No. 2, Carnegie Steel Co. and Pacific Coal Co./Combine, T2662 and T1998, 1922; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Ranger, Combine T2111, 1903-1935; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Robert Jenkins, T.M. Jenkins & Co./National Trans. Co., T2179, 1881-1924; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Sailor, J&L Steel Co., T2226, 1924-1951; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Sam Barnum, Hillman Coal & Coke Co., T2238, 1912-1917; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Swan, U.S. Corps of Engineers, T2367, June 9, 1915; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 50)
- T.P. Roberts, U.S. corps of Engineers, T2382, 1906-1926; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Thomas Moses, Carnegie-Illinois Steel Co., T2419, 1936-1957; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Titan, J&L Steel Co., T2443, 1930-1953; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Vesta, J&L Steel Co., T2521, 1931-1948; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Vulcan, J&L Steel Co., T2550, 1910-1951; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 55)
- W.C. Jutte, Peoples Coal Co. +3 co. later, T2555, 1901-1917; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Warren Elsey, J&L Steel Co., T2613, 1919-1953; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 57)
- W.C. Sutherland, Hillman Trans. Co., T2653, 1936-1939; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Wm. Larimer Jones, J&L Steel Co., T2671, 1930-1953; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 59)
- W.P. Snyder, Carnegie Steel/Crucible Fuel Co., T2587, 1945-1953; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Wilmot, T2691, 1900-1907 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Youghiogheny, Carnegie Steel Co., T2707, 1927-1935; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 62)